Edith Benham Helm Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edith Benham Helm Papers 1915-1961
MSS25700
Helm, Edith Benham, 1874-1962
10,000 items
28 containers plus 4 oversize
14 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Social secretary at the White House. Letters, notes, scrapbooks, and photographs documenting Helm's career as social secretary at the White House during the Woodrow Wilson, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Harry S. Truman administrations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Helm, Edith Benham, 1874-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Organizations
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); White House (Washington, D.C.)
Subjects
World War, 1914-1918--Peace.
Places
Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Social secretaries.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Edith Benham Helm, social secretary at the White House, were given to the Library of Congress by Helm between 1940 and 1962.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edith Benham Helm are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1874 Born, Staten Island, N.Y.
1915 1919 Social secretary to Edith Bolling Galt Wilson
1919 Accompanied the presidential party to the Peace Conference, Paris, France
1920 Married Rear Admiral James M. Helm (died 1927)
1933 1953 White House social secretary to Eleanor Roosevelt and Bess Wallace Truman
1954 Published The Captains and the Kings. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons
1962, Aug. 7 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edith Benham Helm (1874-1962) span the years 1915-1961 and pertain to her career as social secretary to the White House during the administrations of Woodrow Wilson, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Harry S. Truman. The papers are organized into three series: Paris Peace Conference, White House Scrapbooks, and Miscellany.
Among the items in Paris Peace Conference series is Edith Benham Helm's daily accounts of her two trips to Europe as a member of the party accompanying President Woodrow Wilson to the Peace Conference in Paris. She served as as secretary to his wife, Edith Bolling Galt Wilson. The White House Scrapbooks include Helms's personal scrapbooks containing invitations and other memorabilia, as well as scrapbooks documenting official social functions at the White House. Among the Miscellany is information about Bess Wallace Truman's activities that were compiled for press briefings.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Paris Peace Conference, 1918-1920
White House Scrapbooks, 1915-1961
Miscellany, 1919-1961
Container List
- Paris Peace Conference, 1918-1920 (Box 1-6)
  Notes, scrapbook, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
  Arranged by type of material
  - Notes (Box 1)
    - Typewritten, Dec. 1918-July 1919, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - Holograph (Box 1)
      - Dec. 1918-May 1919, (7 folders) (Box 1)
      - May-July 1919, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook (Box 2)
    - Photographs, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Photographs, scrapbook (Box OV 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, scrapbook (Box OV 6)
- White House Scrapbooks, 1915-1961 (Box 7-31)
  Scrapbooks containing correspondence, invitations and other memorabilia, and material relating to social functions.
  Arranged according to type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - 7 Mar. 1916-15 May 1951 (Box 7)
    - 5 May 1955-20 Dec. 1961 (Box 7)
  - Invitations and other memorabilia (Box 8)
    - Dec. 1915-May 1930, includes articles Helm wrote for Cosmopolitan about the White House and the Paris Peace Conference, Aug.-Oct. 1930 (Box 8)
    - Nov. 1936-Aug. 1943 (Box 9)
    - Oct. 1937-June 1938, includes “Making the Wheels Go Round” by Eleanor Roosevelt (Box 10)
    - Social events attended by Helm, 1938-1939 (Box 11)
    - Nov. 1939-Sept. 1942 (Box 12)
    - Nov. 1940-Aug. 1941 (Box 13)
    - Oct. 1943-Feb. 1949 (Box 14)
    - Oct. 1944-Dec. 1945 (Box 15)
    - Dec. 1945-Dec. 1947 (Box 16)
    - 1949-Aug. 1950 (Box 17)
    - Oct. 1950-May 1952 (Box 18)
    - May 1952-Sept. 1961 (Box 19)
  - Social functions (Box 20)
    - Mar. 1933-Oct. 1934 (Box 20)
    - Sept. 1934-July 1935 (Box 21)
    - White House season, Aug. 1935-June 1936 (Box OV 22)
    - Social season, 1936-1937 (Box 22)
    - June 1937-June 1938 (Box 23)
    - June 1938-Aug. 1939 (Box 24)
    - Oct. 1939-Aug. 1940 (Box 25)
    - Oct. 1939-Aug. 1940 (Box 26)
    - Oct. 1941-July 1943, (2 volumes) (Box 27)
    - Sept. 1943-May 1945, (2 volumes) (Box 28)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt funeral, 1945 (Box 28)
    - May 1945-July 1947, (2 volumes) (Box 29)
    - Oct. 1947-Sept. 1949, (2 volumes) (Box 30)
    - Oct. 1949-Jan. 1953, (2 volumes) (Box OV 31)
- Miscellany, 1919-1961 (Box 32)
  Press briefing material and accounts of events.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Press briefing material, 1945-1953 (Box 32)
  - Accounts of events (Box 32)
    - Report of conversations concerning the resignation of Secretary of State Robert Lansing, 18 Feb. 1920 (Box 32)
    - Lord Grey not being received at White House, newspaper clipping, and note to Benham from D. Tynell, undated (Box 32)
    - Craufurd-Stuart Affair, memorandum, 1919 (Box 32)
    - Memorandum concerning Madame Chiang-Kai-Chek, 1961 (Box 32)